# NIKOS DANIILIDIS

www: http://nikosd.me

linkedin: https://www.linkedin.com/in/ndaniilidis

e-mail: nikos.daniilidis@gmail.com

Phone: (510) 495-7126

#### **PROFILE**

Scientist committed to extracting insights from data-intensive applications.

Background: atomic physics, condensed matter physics, electrical & computer engineering Expertise: scientific programming & data analysis; modelling and characterization of com-

plex processes; computer-aided control and optimization; scientific writing Team worker: worked with large teams building complex experimental setups

Supervisor: guided graduate and undergraduate students in their projects

Presenter: 10+ years experience presenting at conferences & funding-review meetings

Manager: co-authored research grants, helped plan & set up UC Berkeley ion trapping lab

## **EDUCATION**

Ph.D., Physics, Brown University, Providence, RI, 2008, X. S. Ling grroup

Sc.M., Physics, Brown University, Providence, RI, 2003

Diploma, Electrical and Computer Engineering, National Technical University of Athens, Athens, Greece, 2001 (5-year program)

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Post Doc (October 2009–present)

Department of Physics, University of California Berkeley, H. Häffner group

Junior Scientist (September 2007–September 2009)

IQOQI, R. Blatt group, Innsbruck, Austria

Post-Doc (October 2007-January 2008)

ETH, Zürich, A. Wallraff group, Switzerland

## **AWARDS**

Marie Curie Intra European Fellowship for Career Development April 2008–March 2010, European Comission

Forrest Award for Excellent Work Related to Experimental Apparatus

May 2008, Brown University, Providence, RI, USA

Award for Excellence as a Graduate Teaching Assistant

May 2002, Brown University, Providence, RI, USA

#### SKILLS

Scientific programming/Data analysis: Python, Matlab, R, SQL, Hadoop/MapReduce Scientific writing: research articles, review articles, scientific commentaries, grant proposals Modelling/Design: modelling-characterization of noise processes, electromagnetic simulations, computer-aided control, device design & development

Prototype building: rf & digital electronics, microfabrication, lasers, vacuum, cryogenics Characterization: neutron scattering, surface treatment/analysis, low-level measurements

## DATA EXPERIENCE

Data munging: xml, html, json, pdf, text

Data manipulation: Python Pandas, R, Matlab, SQL, Hadoop/MapReduce

Machine learning: Python scikit-learn, R

Projects: http://nikosd.me/projects/index.html Github: https://github.com/nikos-daniilidis Bloq: http://oligotropos.wordpress.com/

## PROFESSIONAL ACHIEVEMENTS

- ⋈ Co-authored grants, worth in excess of \$ 1 M
- № Participated in planning/building UC Berkeley ion trapping group
- ⋈ Conducted/Analyzed data-intensive experiments: ion trap, neutron scattering, ultrasonics
- ⋈ Coauthored fourteen publications (see http://nikosd.me/publications/index.html)
- ⋈ Developped methods/algorithms/Matlab library for ion-trap electrostatic control

(https://github.com/HaeffnerLab/trap-simulation-tools-matlab)

- Guided, coordinated Python translation of library for ion-trap electrostatic control (https://github.com/HaeffnerLab/trap-simulation-tools-python-27)
- M Developped, fabricated ion-trap chips for UC Berkeley, MIT, Uni Mainz, Uni Innsbruck
- ▶ Designed & built Surface-Science/Ion-trapping/UHV system
- □ Designed cryostat for ion trapping
- $\bowtie$  Designed & built cryogenic calorimeter

# **HOBBIES**

Dancing, hiking, open-sea swimming, the outdoors